这卤正合适 嗨这鸡蛋打的
The gravy is just right. Hey - you see the egg is so nice
# 初二面 打卤面
Second day (of the Chinese New Year), noodles' day, Da Lu Mian (lit. noodles with thick gravy topping)
# 来了  三位师爷吉祥
There you are, wish you luck Shiye!
# 欢子来啦  给您拜年啦
Huanzi's here, wish you a happy New Year!
# 向师爷学打卤面来啦
You came here to learn cooking Dalu Mian, didn't you?
# 师爷打卤面有名
Shiye's got a fame in cooking Dalu Mian
# 这块肉就够了  咱把它煮了吧
This lump of meat will be enough. Let's boil it.
# 屁股蛋儿（后臀尖）坐水煮
Sit in the water and boil
# 你看咱们先把料加里
You see, we first put in the side ingredients
# 葱姜加上 然后搁点花椒
Scallions and ginger, then a few peppercorns
# 又肥又瘦正合适 是吧
It has the right proportion of fat, doesn't it?
# 你要五花肉就太肥
If you use pork belly, it has too much fat
# 还可以搁一大料瓣  多了不行
You can also use no more than one full Da Liao Ban (star anise in Beijing dialect)
# 大料瓣煮到一半的时候
Take away the star anise when it's half way through cooking
# 就把它捞起来 就不要了
scoop it out and throw it away
# 二伯煮多长时间 四十分钟
- Er Bai, how long does it take to cook the pork? - 40 minutes.
# 炸丸子
to fry meatballs
# 大爷他们家海米好
Da Ye's dried shrimps are of high quality
# 我先尝尝 你尝吧
- I'll have a taste first. - Help yourself.
# 今天这打卤跟咱们原先的
Today this gravy is a bit different
# 有点不一样
from what we saw previously
# 海米泡好后剁碎加到肉馅里
Chop the dried shrimps when they have soaked up, and mix with the chopped meat
# 师爷这打卤是创新的
Shiye's gravy is an innovative version
# shift backward 00:00:05,800
# 打卤面里边加点小丸子
Add some little meatballs to the gravy
# 咱就肉 我就稍微剁一点剁下筋
Let's get the meat. I'm gonna chop the tendon for a bit
# 这什么肉 五花肉
- What kind of meat is it? - Pork belly
# 剁好没有别跟这儿团糊了
Have you finished chopping? Don't mess it up.  # (团糊了是什么状态?)
# 打馅  葱姜水
Ready for tossing. Scallion and ginger water -
# 葱姜水有个三十克
We need about 30g
# 好  使劲攉拢攉拢
Good. Mix and stir thoroughly
# 搁点黄酒
Add some yellow cooking wine
# 滴滴的香油增加香气
A few drops of seasame oil to increase the flavour
# 搁的胡椒粉
Add some pepper powder
# 盐少来一点就行了
It's ok with less salt
# 味不要太重这个说对了
You're right about not making the taste too heavy
# 这个是泡香菇的原汤
This is the water used to soak shiitake mushrooms
# 你看倒点香菇水 这是关键点
You see, the crucial point is adding the shiitake water
# 泡香菇最好的是用
The best for soaking up shiitakes
# 开水和凉水配比的水
is water neither too hot or too cold
# 凉水不容易激发出来它那香气
Cold water does not help bringing out the aroma
# 开水香气它给闷在里边
Boiled water would lock the aroma inside
# 所以说泡香菇的香气
Thus the aroma of shiitakes
# 最适合的温度是五十五度
The best temperature to bring it out is 55°C
# 这个香气整个释放出来了
This aroma, the whole of it goes out
# 我的现在给普及一下
These I now teach you
# 烧油吧  您是炸是汆啊
Heat up the oil. Are you gonna fry or boil them?
# 少来点粉子  炸啊大爷
- Less starch. - To fry of course, Da Ye
# 玉米淀粉 摔摔它
Corn starch. Toss it a few times
# 行  小欢子行
Not bad, little Huanzi's doing good
# 三叔给开油烟机 好
- San Shu, would you open the range hood? - Sure
# 老大不支老二直接支老三了
The eldest skips the second-eldest to order the youngest
# 指使不动你
His words have no effect on you
(laughters)
# 行了这点油够了
Ok, the oil is enough
# 三叔家的油 真使啊
San Shu's oil, you're so generously using it
# 油温可以了啊 再不炸就完蛋了
The temperature is ok. Start frying or things will be spoiled.
# 炸成小丸子
Fry the meatballs
# 火大点 三叔火大点
Increase the heat, San Shu, turn up the fire
# 欢子这小丸子炸的还可以啊
The meatballs fried by Huanzi are not bad
# 金黄
It's golden
# 复炸了
Second frying
# 复查一次 复炸一次就行
fry once again, one time is fine
# 炸完了以后搁点大料
After that add some spices
# 搁点葱姜酒一蒸 比这烧还好
Steaming with some scallion, ginger, and wine would work better than braising
# 这小丸子炸的不错
The frying of meatballs is good
# 不错
Nice
# 口蘑 不要太薄
White mushrooms - don't slice them too thin
# 这样就正合适 好
This is just right, good
# 洗木耳 抓点盐洗木耳
Wash the wood ears. Grab some salt
# 用盐杀一下
Clean it with salt
# 你看它的黑的全下来了 脏物
You see those black dirts are all removed
# 这一勺搁进去
Put in the whole spoon of salt
# 搁进去 都搁进去 行
All, all of it, okay
# 靠一边 拿手直接攥 攥是吗 对
- Leave it (salt can) aside. Grip and stir with your hands. - Grip and stir right? - Yep
# 十几年真的第一次见
This is my first time seeing in over ten years
# 这么处理木耳的
such a way of preparing tree fungus
# 看见没有
Don't you see
# 黑渣子出来了吧
The black dirts are coming out
# 然后再冲 就行了
And you rinse it
# 赶紧冲 就是脆的
Rinse immediately, and the wood ears would be crispy
# 又脆又好吃
Crispy and tasty
# 咱这水呢 泡香菇的水留着
We keep this water soaking shiitakes
# 待会打卤使
It'll be used to cook the gravy
# 这底下呢 就脏
It's dirty down in the bottom
# 是吧
Isn't it
# 这水咱就不要了
We will leave that part
# 拿勺淀粉就行了 对
Get a spoon of starch. There you go.
# 生抓 抓完了之后
Grip and stir, after that
# 就把那泥沙给带出去了
The mud and sand will be taken away
# 攥 使劲
Grip, harder
# 拿大拇哥揉一下
Rub the surface of shiitakes
# 平菇上的面
with your thumb
# 你看 这洗完了透亮不透亮
You see, aren't they clean and bright
# 亮晶晶
Shining with water
# 斜刀一片一刀 对太小了这就
Slant-cut into two pieces, right. Too small, this one is
# 根儿去吗  根儿不去
- The stem, should I remove it? - No
# 其实没事挺香的
It doesn't matter. The stems are aromatic
# 原来我们穷的时候专门买根吃
In the past, without much money, we just bought the stem.
# 这根其实比肉还香
The stem is actually more tasty than meat.
# 我觉得先把丸子给烧上
I think we should boil the meatballs in advance
# 这黄花水也不扔 这好东西
We're keeping this daylily water, good stuff
# 你先洗两遍再去泡发
Wash two times before soaking them
# 中间斩一刀
Cut right in the middle
多放底油葱段姜片大料瓣 煸炒
Put in more base oil and stir-fry scallions, ginger slices, and star anises
# 下丸子你看
Drop the meatballs in, you see
# 先拿酱油炝上香味来
Put in the light soy sauce to stimulate the flavour
# 还得来
More
大动作的是吧
What a movement, huh?
# 少搁汤那边还有肉汤呢
Don't put in too much water. We got meat soup over there
# 菌菇汤黄花汤 三汤
Soup combo of fungus, mushrooms, and daylily, soup of three
# 三叔 你家这酒快没了
San Shu, you're running out of wine
# 黄花水 好喽
Daylily water, cool
# 香菇水
Shiitake water
# 先烧一会 全是亮点
Braise it a while, all eye-catching stuff
# 料也可以下锅了
It's ready for the side-ingredients
# 不用等开 对等什么开啊
- You don't need to wait until it's boiling. - This is true. Boiling for what?
# 肉已经四十分钟了好了
The meat has been cooked for 40 minutes. It's done
# 就能切薄点么再 切薄点
Could you cut it thinner?
# 太厚了 再薄点
Too thick. Thinner
# 烫死我了  你再泡会儿
- It's boiling hot! -Soak it again in the water for a while
# 三叔你看这么薄可以吗 可以
- San Shu you see, is this thin enough? - Okay
# 您这太可以了
More than okay
# 就是这点肉 这就够了
This bit of meat is enough
# 颜色浅不浅啊 找颜色就行
Have we got the right colour?
# 不行 还得多来吧
Nah, we need more (dark soy sauce)
# 吃就吃酱油味 加点（酱油）
We're just looking for the taste of soy sauce. Add a bit more (soy sauce)
# 胡椒粉 放你的
Pepper powder, there you go
# 先勾芡是先搁鸡蛋啊
Should we first thicken the gravy or put in the eggs?
# 先勾芡 二伯真反应过来了
Gravy first. Er Bai's got that
# 一勺不行 像你这样得三勺（盐）
One spoon won't do. Like this you need three spoons of salt
# 再来一勺
One more spoon
# 全攉拢攉拢倒吧
Stir and mix a bit. Pour it out anyway
# 往一个方向欢子你知道吗
Stir in one direction. Huanzi, you got this?
# 要不乱汤
Otherwise the soup would be spoiled
# 全倒进去吧
Pour out all of it
# 二伯今儿是炒肝的勾芡方法
Today Er Bai is using the way of making gravy in Stir-fried livers
# 一个方向推
Push in the same direction
# 转圈推
Push in a circle
# 托大片儿啊
Ready for the eggs # (我猜的)
# 稠度够吗
Is it thick enough
# 稠度够了 这合适
This is just right
# 够了啊
Okay cool
# 你托吧 我给你抖搂锅
You get the eggs. I'll be shaking the wok
# 先别动
Don't touch it
# 待会起不来片儿了
Or the eggs would lose the shape
# 你看 片儿起来了
You see, the eggs are floating
# 慢慢慢慢
Slowly
# 看见没有 一下托底啊
Don't you see? # 看不懂什么叫“一下托底”
# 这回差不多了
Now this should be done
# 你看了没有
Have a look
# 颜色合适
The colour should be right
# 味道得足
The flavour has to be strong
# 这种正合适
This is perfect
# 嘿 这鸡蛋打的 合适
Hey - you see the egg is so nice
# 把这卤先搁后边 先切点葱花啊
Leave the gravy aside for a while. Let's chop some scallions
# 得 我来
Sure. I got this
# 三叔给下上面了
San Shu's cooking the noodles
# 下面讲究盖着盖
Put the lid on the wok when cooking the noodles
# 光搁这油不行
This oil won't work
# 两种油才香
You need two kinds of oil for the best aroma
# 二油合一 香油 混合油
Two kinds of oil in one, mixed oil with seasame oil
# 炸出那花椒才香气十足
So that the peppercorns could have the best aroma
# 北京花椒没那么麻
The numbness of Beijing peppercorn is not very strong
# 它有那种香气味
It has the aromatic flavour instead
# 卤拿出来
Get the gravy
# 把那葱搁上去
And spread the chopped scallions upon it
# 够了啊 足够了
This is enough
# 好了 行了
Well, well
# 这就足够
This is all fine
# 你看这香气味出来了
You see the aroma is coming out
# 两种油的混合油
Mixed oil with two kinds of oil
# 看似简单 你看
It looks simple, you see
# 初一饺子初二面 面上来了
Dumplings for the first day, noddles for the second. Here's the noodles
# 够了
Enough
# 来 大爷您看 尝尝 好吃
Come on, Da Ye you see. Have a taste. Very tasty
# 我天哪 太香了
My God! It smells so good
# 今天咱们吃锅挑儿
Today we're gonna have "Guo Tiao'er"
(Guo Tiao'er: noodles picked from the pot and eaten immediately with the gravy)
# 咸不咸 正好
- Is it too salty? - Spot on
# 三叔 怎么样三叔
San Shu, how is it?
# 您这这徒孙做的怎么样
How does your grand-apprentice's work taste?
# 正好 徒孙出徒了 谢谢师爷们
- It's just right! Your apprenticeship is completed. - Thank you Shi Ye!
# shift forward 00:00:05,800
# import ending.srt 00:08:05,600